# 哈喽大家好
Hello, everybody.
# 今天停电我四伯爷用他剩的几斤糯米
Today the power went out, and my uncle has some sticky rice left.
# 煮来我们今天做糯米糍粑
We will make some glutinous rice cakes today.
# 我小时候吃过
I ate them when I was a kid.
# 今天四伯爷教我
Uncle will teach me how to make it today.
# 回忆一下小时候的味道
Reminisce about the taste of my childhood.
# 这个米我们泡的时间不够就燎（煮）了一下
We didn't soak this rice long enough, so we decided to boil it before steaming.
# 我四伯说燎一下更好
My uncle says it's better to start with boiling.
# 这个糯米是甜的噶
This glutinous rice is sweet.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 这个要插一些洞洞噶
Why need to poke some holes?
# 气眼都嘛
It's for ventilation (more uniform heating).
# 今天我们准备了黄豆还有这个芝麻 白糖
Today we also prepared soybeans, sesame seed and white sugar.
# 这两个是用来过炒噶
These will be toasted.
# 嗯 炒
Yeah.
# 等一下把这两个炒香
Toast these up later.
# 炒香了之后用那个小碓窝把它舂碎
Crush them with that stone mortar after toasting.
# 舂碎了 这个糍粑弄好了之后
Crushed. Once the rice cakes are done...
# 我们这边是吃热的
We serve them hot here in my hometown.
# 出来了就弄来扯起就开始吃
We will start eating right away when it's ready.
# 蘸点这个再弄点白糖和（拌）哈
Dip the rice cake in the sugar.
# 而且还有这个糍粑在我们这里还有一个谚语
And there's an old saying about this rice cake in our area.
# 猫抓糍粑 叫什么呢
What's the saying? Like cat something?
# 猫抓糍粑脱不了爪爪
If a cat touches the rice cake, it won't be able to pull out its paw.
# 是啥子意思
What does that mean?
# 猫去抓那个糍粑嘛 一抓到就粘起得你咋子脱得到爪爪呢
The rice cake is so sticky that even an agile cat won't be able to get it off its paw.
# 你就脱不到撒
Cat won't get it off.
# 但是那个打糍粑越打得融越好
The harder you pound the rice the better.
# 越舂得久越好
The longer the pounding, the better.
# 随便你好多力气都给你用得完
You need to use up as much strength as you have.
# 是不哦
Really?
# 是啊
Yeah.
# 越用得大的力气越舂得久就越是融和
The more force you use, the longer you pound it, the more glutinous it becomes!
# 四伯爷你看我这个肌肉舂得到好久
Uncle, how long do you think these muscles can last?
# 半个小时吧
Half an hour.
# 半个小时呀
Half an hour?
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 太小看我了嘛
You're underestimating me.
# 太小看你 你舂哈看嘛半个小时
No no, you try pounding for half an hour!
# 我是练过的哦
I've been trained.
# 练过的啊 那东西累人得很
Trained? It's still exhausting.
# 洒点水它才更融和
It'll blend better with some water.
# 都好像好了一样
It's like it's ready.
# 好好可以了
Okay, okay.
# 我尝一点看
Let me try some.
# 盖上再蒸哈
Cover and steam it a bit more.
# 已经熟了
It's ready.
# 是啊 再等会儿更融和点
Yeah, let it rest for a bit and it would be more glutinous.
# 看来我们这个都不用40分钟
Looks like we don't need to steam it for 40 minutes
# 可能20分钟都够了
Maybe 20 minutes is enough.
# 因为我们刚才燎了一下米就比较软
Because the rice is softer after we just boiled it.
# 直接倒里面哦
Just pour it in.
# 嗯 倒里面
Yeah, in there.
# 好不好倒哦
Are you sure?
# 翻过来直接倒下去就是
Turn it over and it will fall straight down.
# 干起 干起 干起
Let's go, let's go!
# 沾点水
Dip it in water first.
# 四伯爷我来试一下看
Let me do it, Uncle.
# 融得很
Blend well.
# 安逸得很
It's so nice.
# 时不时都要沾水哦
You have to dip it in water every now and then.
# 不沾水要粘起
Otherwise all the rice will stick to the mallet.
# 才舂几下就舂耙了
Just a few minutes and it's already soft and sticky.
# 就可以了吗 不舂了啊
Is that enough? No more pounding?
# 我还没舂呢 让我舂两下看
I haven't pounded it yet. Let me give it a try.
# 好 你舂嘛 舂嘛
Okay, you pound it... pound it...
# 我这个工具人还没发挥呢
I'm a useful apprentice.
# 哇
Wow.
# 这个糍粑粘得我动都不好动
It's so sticky I can't even pull it up.
# 看嘛
See?
# 这个糍粑好安逸哦
It's so nice.
# 诶呀 好累哦
I'm so tired.
# 看嘛
See?
# 这个要有点力气哦 没得点力气还不行
This one requires some strength. You can't do it without strength.
# 诶呀 好大一坨
Oh my, what a big lump.
# 都闻到香味了
I can smell the aroma.
# 好 都可以了四伯爷
Good, it's ready, Uncle.
# 你尝一下看
You want to try it?
# 我整不动
My teeth can't handle it.
# 我给你舂了来 你就整得动了
I'll pound it for you and you'll be able to eat it.
# 你该叫师弟嘛 你喊漆二娃
You should get Jieping to help, not Qi Erwa.
# 我看你在那里站起耍都嘛
I see you're just standing there.
# 芝麻更香
Sesame is even more fragrant.
# 芝麻还香点
Sesame seeds smell so good.
# 好 吃糍粑了
Okay, let's eat the rice cake.
# 搞起搞起管它的了一会儿是吃不完的
Let's eat it, I cannot wait.
# 我们准备吃糍粑了
We're ready to eat it!
# 这个四伯爷教我的这样子转一下
Uncle taught me how to do this, you need to turn it like this.
# 然后粘上（白糖）
Then coat it with some sugar.
# 我以前吃那种 外面卖的那种糖就是这样搅的
I used to have something similar that they sell on the street.
# 麦芽糖
Maltose?
# 看嘛这糍粑好安逸嘛
Look at this rice cake. So nice.
# 嗯不错
Yeah, that's good.
# 好舒服嘛吃起
It feels good. Eat it.
# 这个糯米真的有点好
This glutinous rice is really good.
# 果然是我们小时候的味道
It tastes just like childhood.
# 安逸
Nice!
# 安逸噶
Very Nice!
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 你年轻的时候吃得到几碗哦
How many bowls were you able to eat when you were young?
# 这么大一坨
This big lump.
# 这么大一坨啊
That big?
# 2斤啊
2 jin (1 kg)?
# 肯定吃得完撒2斤
I'm sure I can finish 2 jin, no problem!
# 你不怕吃来不消化啊
Aren't you afraid that you won't be able to digest it?
# 不得呀
Oh, no.
# 你不信你好久去街上买2斤给我吃哈看嘛
If you don't believe me, go buy me 2 jin of it from the street!
# 看我吃得完不嘛
You'll see if I can finish it.
# 我这个时候都吃得完
I can eat it all even at this age.
# 你伯爷吃饮食凶得很
Your uncle is a furious eater.
# 下次整点饭米在里面
Next time, put some regular rice in it.
# 这次的太糯很了
It's too sticky this time.
# 牙齿都要粘掉
My teeth are almost pulled out.
# 那不是咋子安成本太高了
It's also very expensive.
# 如果大家想吃得话可以在家里试一下
You can try it at home if you want.
# 其实很简单的
It's really quite simple.
# 只要把这个米泡几个小时再蒸
Just soak some sticky rice for a few hours and then steam it.
# 蒸熟了之后直接把它捣碎
Steam it and then pound it.
# 把它捣成泥
Pound it into one piece.
# 然后把黄豆和芝麻炒香再捣碎
Then roast the soybeans and sesame seeds and crush them.
# 再放点白糖一起拌一下
Put some sugar in it and mix it up.
# 用这个蘸一下就可以吃了
Dip the rice in and eat it.
# 要吃甜点就多放一点白糖
If you like it sweet, put more sugar in the dip.
# 不吃甜一点就少放一点白糖
If you don't like it sweet, use less sugar.
# 只是吃法不同
There are many ways to eat rice cakes.
# 城市里面大家都喜欢冷了之后切成块再来煎一下
In the city, people like to let the rice cakes cool down, cut them into chunks and deep fry.
# 然后再淋点红糖上去
And then add brown sugar syrup on top.
# 但是我们农村就是这样打好了马上就趁热吃
This is the way we do it in the countryside, eat it while it's hot.
# 蘸着这个吃
Dip it in this.
# 还是不错噶
It's very good.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 好了本期视频就到这里
All right, that's it for this video.
# 拜拜
Bye-bye.
# 大家可以在家里试一下
You can try it at home.